<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Helmingham in Suffolk, June 30th, 1694, at the funeral of L. Gen. Tolmach by Nicholas Brady ...</title>
            <author>Brady, Nicholas, 1659-1726.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4177</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12115599</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12115599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54284</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29158)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54284)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 759:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Helmingham in Suffolk, June 30th, 1694, at the funeral of L. Gen. Tolmach by Nicholas Brady ...</title>
                  <author>Brady, Nicholas, 1659-1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich. Parker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published at the request of the friends of the deceased."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tollemache, Thomas, 1651?-1694.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54284:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Helmingham</hi> in <hi>Suffolk, June</hi> 30th, 1694. At the FUNERAL OF L. Gen. Tolmach.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nicholas Brady,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of <hi>St. Catherine Cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>-Church,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of the Friends of the deceaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rich. Parker</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn,</hi> under the Piazza of the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:54284:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54284:2"/>
            <head>TO HER GRACE THE Dutcheſs of Lauderdale.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS nothing could excuſe my Confidence, in preſenting this following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to your Grace, but the great ſhare
<pb facs="tcp:54284:3"/>you have in the much lamented occaſion of it; ſo nothing could attone for the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Preſent, but the eager tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of a haſty Zeal; which rather urged me to pay this imperfect Tribute to the Memory of ſo great a Man, than to conſult my own Eaſe or Reputation, by making the ſhortneſs of the warning my juſt excuſe, for waving an Employment as difficult as honourable.</p>
            <p>To do tolerable Juſtice to ſo deſerving a Theme, required a larger portion both of Time and Ability, than I had either the good fortune to enjoy, or the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to pretend to; and if I have but teſtified my veneration for his Memory, which every <hi>True Engliſhman</hi> will joyn with me in doing, it is the only Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that I aim at, from a performance as hearty as it is inartificial.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54284:3"/>
            <p> I queſtion not, but your Grace will add to all your other Virtues, that of a chearful reſignation to the will of God; and give a freſh evidence of the firmneſs of that Courage, which has formerly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported you under the greateſt Trials. Eſpecially ſince, to ſweeten and temper the bitterneſs of your loſs, your Grace has the advantage of ſome ſignal conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to ſee your Son conſecrated to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Fame, univerſally regretted by all that knew him, and embalmed with the Tears of that moſt Excellent Princeſs, <hi>in whoſe Service</hi> it was his laſt wiſh <hi>to ſpend another Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any paſſage in the following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (as part of it is directed particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to that end) may be ſerviceable to the leſſening your Grace's Affliction, it will
<pb facs="tcp:54284:4"/>be matter of the greateſt Joy and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>May it pleaſe Your Grace, Your Graces moſt obedient, Moſt faithful, And moſt humble Servant,</hi> N. Brady.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54284:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ECCLES. <hi>VII. Ch. Latter end of the 2</hi> Verſe.</bibl>
                  <p>For that is the end of all Men, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving will lay it to his heart.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF the conſpiring wiſhes of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> could reverſe the immutable Decrees of Heaven; if the moſt eminent and diſtinguiſhing perſonal Accompliſhments, could bribe the grim Meſſenger to delay his Summons; or the moſt elevated Courage and Bravery of Soul, could awe the <hi>King of Terrours</hi> into a favourable compliance; we had not now been met together, to perform our laſt duties to the <hi>ſmall</hi> remains of <hi>This Great Man;</hi> not ſo dearly paid for a remarkable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54284:5"/>Inſtance, of the unavoidable neceſſity of Death to all men; by ſeeing one of the nobleſt of our <hi>Engliſh Worthies</hi> within the ſhort compaſs of a few days ſhrunk into a <hi>Coffin full of duſt and aſhes.</hi> But ſince we are convinced by too ſad an experience, that nothing can exempt from that impartial Sentence, which has paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon all the Sons of <hi>Adam;</hi> ſince the Wiſe and the Fooliſh, the Noble and the Baſe, the Valiant and the Coward, muſt equally ly down in the bed of Corruption, and deſcend together un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſilent Chambers of the Earth; ſince <hi>Death</hi> is thus the neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>the living know that they muſt die;</hi> it will be a uſeful labour to enquire, what advantage may be made by us of ſuch a knowledge, and after what manner we ought <hi>to lay it to our hearts, that Death is the end of all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54284:5"/>
            <p> And indeed it is matter of the juſteſt aſtoniſhment, that Death, which is the entertainment of every day, which endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to refreſh our memory of it, by ſuch repeated inſtances of its unavoidable certainty; that ſpeaks to us out of the mouth of every dead man, and reads us a Lecture out of every Coffin; ſhould yet almoſt utterly be loſt to our remembrance, ſhould fall ſo very ſeldom under our ſerious conſideration: and therefore the wiſe Man had ſufficient reaſon to inform us, as he does at the beginning of this Verſe, that <hi>it is better to go to the houſe of morning than to go to the houſe of feaſting,</hi> religious meditations and refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon Death, being at all times a proper and uſeful entertainment; but when we have before us ſuch objects of Mortality, as <hi>This,</hi> which has aſſembled us together at the preſent, contemplations of this nature are neceſſary and indiſpenſable, the ſolemnity of the occaſion calls for them loudly, and forcebly exacts them at our hands; and as our deceaſed bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54284:6"/>ſeems to preach to us this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> That <hi>that is the end of all men;</hi> ſo every well inſtructed Chriſtian will be ready to make this ſober <hi>Application,</hi> That <hi>the living will lay it to his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Death</hi> is the period of every <hi>Life,</hi> that we muſt all die and return unto our Duſt; is a truth acknowledged ſo univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, and ſo undeniably verified by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant experience, that it is needleſs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce arguments for the proof of that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, which none have the confidence or the folly to deny; I ſhall not therefore loſe my time and abuſe your patience, in the unneceſſary confirmation of this eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Maxime, that <hi>Death is the end of all men;</hi> but ſhall wholly confine my follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, to the inference which the wiſe Man draws from thence, that <hi>the living will lay it to his heart;</hi> by ſhewing what uſeful deductions may be made, from a due reflecton upon the certainty of Death, in order to influence our lives and converſations.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54284:6"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then, from a due reflecton upon the certainty of Death, we may learn this leſſon of inſtruction; that, ſince Death is the common lot of all mankind, and ſome time or other we muſt ſubmit to it, we ought therefore to be always ſo prepared to meet it, as that we may at any time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo it willingly and chearfully.</p>
            <p>Indeed if all our care and apprehenſion, if all our carefulneſs and concern, could enable us to avoid the ſtroke of Deſtiny, there were then ſome reaſon for us, to be anxious and ſolicitous upon that occaſion; but ſince this is an irreverſible Decree which has paſt upon all the race of mankind, a wiſe man will make a vertue of neceſſity, by endeavouring to manage himſelf after ſuch a rate, as may make this dreadful Enemy of humane nature, appear leaſt formidable and affrighting: He will at leaſt attempt to diſarm him of his Sting; and that can be done no other way, but by lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54284:7"/>a life unblameable and inoffenſive: we are aſſured, that <hi>the ſting of Death is ſin,</hi> it is that only which makes his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to very terrible; let us but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our ſelves upon that ſide, and we may then meet him with aſſurance and ſatisfaction: Nothing will rejoice us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>Death-bed,</hi> ſo much as the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a well ſpent <hi>life;</hi> all outward Conſolations ſhall then drop a way; our Riches can purchaſe nothing for us, but a Coffin and a Windingſheet; our Friends can only weep by our Bed-ſide, attend us to our Grave, and ly down there and lament over us; our Honours will but ſerve to adorn our Hearſe, and to lay us in the duſt with greater Pomp and Page<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antry; but a Life that has been led Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and Devoutly, this will ſupport us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our laſt conflict, will ſtrengthen and ſuſtain us in our mortal Agonies, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to confront Death in its moſt ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhape, not only with courage but with comfort alſo: Every good action which we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54284:7"/>have at any time performed, will then adminiſter to us joy and ſatisfaction; and if we have conſtantly perſevered in well doing, we ſhall have nothing to ruffle or diſcompoſe us; our paſſage out of this World will be eaſie and agreeable; we ſhall ly down in Death as to a ſweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, from whence we ſhall awake into everlaſting happineſs; and ſhall cloſe our eyes with that triumphant exclamation, <hi>O Death, where is thy Sting? O Grave, where is thy Victory?</hi> Thus is it the Office of true wiſdom, to make that eaſie and familiar to us, which we know is not poſſibly to be avoided; ſince tho we hang back never ſo much, and are never ſo unwilling to be acquainted with it, yet ſtill Death follows us cloſe at the heels, and will at laſt infallibly overtake us. But nothing will more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually prepare us for our end, than to have it continually in our thoughts; that whenever it comes to ſeize on us it may not be new to us, and add to its other terrours the fright of a ſurpriſe: Things the moſt terrible and frightful in their nature,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54284:8"/>become eaſie and ſupportable by our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſed to them; and ſo we ſhall find it in <hi>Death</hi> its ſelf: He who lives <hi>every day</hi> as if that were <hi>his laſt,</hi> will never be unprovided when <hi>his laſt day</hi> comes; he who contemplates upon his end frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, will receive Death when ever it calls upon him, as an acquaintance whom he has long converſed with, and whoſe nearer appreoaches he has expected hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: whereas that man who makes it his buſineſs, to put off that evil hour (as he ſtiles it) far from him, never to fix his thoughts upon the conſideration of it, will be ſtrangely ſtartled and diſcompoſed at its appearance, he will not know how to give reception, to a an intruding rugged <hi>Gueſt,</hi> whoſe viſit is as <hi>unwelcome</hi> as it was <hi>unexpected,</hi> and yet whoſe diſtaſtful compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he cannot poſſibly avoid. And indeed, when the good man has accuſtomed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſome time, to a due conſideration of his latter end, he will not meet with any thing elſe in it, but matter of delight and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54284:8"/>ſatisfaction; it will only appear, as an <hi>ill-looked Jaylor,</hi> that comes to <hi>releaſe him</hi> out of a <hi>hard captivity;</hi> as a <hi>ſurly meſſenger,</hi> that is ſent upon a <hi>welcome errand;</hi> or as a <hi>rough guſt of Wind,</hi> that blows him into <hi>the Harbour:</hi> He has ſo fully reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the certainty of Death, that he has made it his buſineſs to be ready for it whenſoever it ſhall come; and can lay down his life chearfully and contentedly, becauſe <hi>he has the aſſurance of taking it up again,</hi> as knowing <hi>it is but hid with Chriſt in God.</hi> Thus a due reflection upon the certainty of Death, will inſtruct us in this leſſon of true Wiſdom; that we ſhould at all times be qualified to look Death in the Face, without being terrified at it, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided for it. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another leſſon of true Wiſdom which may be learnt from a due reflection upon the certainty of Death, is this; that ſince our continuance in this world cannot laſt for ever, we ſhould therefore wean
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54284:9"/>our ſelves from too great a fondneſs, for ſuch things as we muſt certainly part with at the laſt.</p>
            <p>Being rationally convinced, that all the enjoyments of this world muſt at one time or other drop away from us, the common rules of Prudence will then inſtruct us to diſintangle our affections from them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; not to wed and tye our ſelves too cloſely to them; but only to value them ſo far as they are neceſſary to us in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent circumſtances, without fooliſhly placing our chiefeſt happineſs, in the poſſeſſion of thoſe things which we muſt certainly be divorced from; <hi>Riches,</hi> and <hi>Honours,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> and all the enjoyments <hi>of this life,</hi> are ſeldom ſo conſtant as to attend us <hi>to the end of it;</hi> they generally forſake us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we reach the Grave, but it is moſt certain that they cannot accompany us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it; and <hi>there will be no more remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them, within the Land where all things are forgotten;</hi> and how unreaſonably
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54284:9"/>then does that man act, who places all his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in ſuch tranſitory trifles, as muſt ſhortly either leave him, or be left by him? Indeed if it were probable, or but barely poſſible for us, to be always converſant in this Land of the living; we had then ſome reaſon to be careful and ſolicitous, for the delights and conveniencies of this preſent life: But when we are aſſured, that <hi>our years muſt come to an end, as a tale that is told, and that our age is even as nothing;</hi> that we are but <hi>Travellers and Pilgrims</hi> in this world, have no ſure abiding place, no ſettled dwelling or habitation in it, this ſhould teach us, to deal with it, as wayfaring men with the Inns which they bait at; juſt to make uſe of it for our preſent occaſions, without ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting any great intimacy with it, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much concerned what becomes of it when we are gone. For how dreadful muſt Death be to that unwary perſon, who ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects upon the certainty of his leaving this world, that he never attempts to diſengage himſelf from it? How will that clog and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumber
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54284:10"/>him in his flight? and how hardly will his ſoul be able to get looſe, with ſuch a weight of earth about it? To ſuch a man as this, <hi>Death comes arrayed in all his pomp of Terror;</hi> to take him from the world, is to tear him from himſelf; he is grown (as it were) one piece with it, being rivetted to it by all the ties of intereſt and inclination; and to ſeparate him from that his beloved companion, is like another divorce of Soul and Body: whereas that ſerious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering man, who has duly repreſented to himſelf, that Death will call upon him ſome time or other, and that then he muſt leave behind him all the gaieties of this World; will never be ſo beſotted with the love of them, as to doat upon thoſe things which he muſt one day renounce; and the loſs of which will be ſo much the more <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous,</hi> by how much the more deeply he is <hi>enamoured</hi> of them. Thus will a due refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the certainty of <hi>Death,</hi> give to us that are <hi>living</hi> this moſt uſeful inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that we ſhould wean our ſelves from
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54284:10"/>the vanities of this preſent life, and diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our ſelves from too extravagant a fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for them. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another leſſon of inſtruction which we may be taught by a due reflection upon the certainty of Death, is this; that ſince that is the end of all men living, we ſhould therefore look back upon the occaſion of it; and ſeriouſly conſider, by what means it prevails, ſo univerſally upon all mankind.</p>
            <p>Man was created in a ſtate of <hi>Immortality</hi> as well as <hi>Innocency;</hi> and after a long and happy life in <hi>this world,</hi> would have been tranſlated into <hi>another,</hi> without any uneaſie paſſage through the gates of Death: but when ſin entred into the world, Death al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo entred <hi>with it and by it;</hi> and took its o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal commiſſion for deſtroying, from God's primitive Curſe upon our diſobedience: and indeed they are now linked together ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably, that they always advance hand in hand; and as the world has daily grown more ſinfull, ſo Death alſo has grown more
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54284:11"/>powerful; has daily made its more near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches; and <hi>our life which paſſes away as a ſhadow,</hi> like that upon the Dial of <hi>Ahaz, has gone backwards.</hi> For tho' Death is the moſt dreadful enemy of humane nature, yet our darling ſins, however they may ſeem to flatter and cajoll us, keep up a moſt ſtrict League and Correſpondence with it; every embrace they ſeem to give us, does but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the inſlaving us to this potent Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and every kiſs, like that of <hi>Judas,</hi> does but betray us into Ruine and Deſtruction; all thoſe enjoyments with which they ſeem to treat us, are but ſo many inlets to the Grave, and ſo many entrances into the chambers of Death: Thoſe are they, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>gay and lightſome they</hi> may appear, which labour to deprive us of the <hi>light of the Sun,</hi> to lay us down in <hi>darkneſs and in ſilence,</hi> to throw us amongſt mouldring Bones and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifying Carkaſes, and to make us the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of Rottenneſs and Corruption: all our beloved boſome tranſgreſſions, are but ſo many bewitching <hi>Dalilahs,</hi> which lull our heads in their laps, and rock us into a Lethargy;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54284:11"/>that ſo they may give us up bound and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, into the hands of our moſt mortal ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. And can we then be employed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of this nature, can we believe that <hi>Death is the wages of ſin,</hi> not only a Salary that will <hi>certainly</hi> be paid, but ſuch a one as ought <hi>in juſtice</hi> to be ſo, as if we had <hi>bargained</hi> and <hi>covenanted</hi> for it; without loathing and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating thoſe fatal incendiaries, which have ſet us at enmity with our God, and have brought Death and deſtruction into the world? If there be any thing in Death that is fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or diſmal, it ought to work in us a ſtrong averſion againſt ſin, which alone has laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us the invincible neceſſity, of entring into a conflict with that formidable Adverſary. This then is another piece of prudence, which is taught us by a due reflection upon the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Death; it engages us to look back upon the cauſe of it, ſin; and to entertain a horror and deteſtation for it. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Another Leſſon of true Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which may be learnt from a due refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the certainty of Death, is this; that ſince nothing can exempt us from the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54284:12"/>Grave, that common receptacle of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane kind; we ſhould therefore be patient and contented under Sickneſs, and bear the Infirmities of this life with a chearful reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Sickneſs is the uſual forerunner of our end, the <hi>commom road</hi> which moſt Men tread, to the <hi>dark Palace</hi> of imperious Death; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to murmor or repine under ſuch diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, is as if we ſhould be angry, at <hi>being put into the way,</hi> which leads directly to our <hi>jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne's end: Diſeaſes</hi> are the general <hi>Harbingers of Mortality,</hi> which come before to marck out thoſe places, where the <hi>great King of Terrours</hi> deſigns to <hi>lodge;</hi> and tho' ſome go off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any warning, and drop out of the World ſuddenly and inſenſibly, yet whether that may be in Mercy or in Judgment, God only knows; ſure I am, that which can but once be done, and the conſequences of which are ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ought to be done very well, and ſickneſs is the ſureſt and moſt effectual <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer,</hi> to put us in mind of dying as we ſhould. It is recorded of <hi>King</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip <hi>the</hi> Macedonian, that leaſt his proſperous
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54284:12"/>eſtate ſhould too far puff him up, he order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one of his Attendants, each morning to remind him of his Mortality, with this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>O King thou muſt die:</hi> and how many of us ſhould be apt to forget our ſelves, did not ſickneſs perform for us this charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble office, and give us a kind <hi>Item</hi> of our periſhing condition! How unjuſt then and ungrateful a proceeding will it be, to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel at the <hi>Viſits</hi> of an obliging <hi>Monitor,</hi> who only comes to refreſh our memory, that we may not be forgetful of our moſt valuable concernments? how heavy or intolerable ſoever our preſſures may appear, yet Death (we are ſure) whoſe meſſengers they are, will not fail quickly to put an end to them; and can we not then bear, with a quiet reſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thoſe things that bring with them ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable an advantage, and whoſe remedy is ſo certain, and ſo near? How unfit is that man to look Death <hi>in the face,</hi> who cannot bear its moſt <hi>diſtant approaches?</hi> or to ſtruggle with <hi>mortal Agonies</hi> and <hi>Convulſions'</hi> that ſhrinks under the firſt aſſault of an <hi>Ague</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54284:13"/>or a <hi>Feaver?</hi> whereas that conſtant and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved mind, which chearfully ſubmits to the hand of God, and breaks the force of his diſtemper by a Chriſtian patience; is by <hi>theſe lighter tryals</hi> exerciſed and prepared, to ſtand the ſhock of the <hi>grand encounter;</hi> he becomes familiar and acquainted with Death, by converſing calmly with its friends and companions, and can never be ſtartled at its <hi>Perſonal appearance,</hi> when he has thus been uſed to correſpond with it, by the interpoſition of its <hi>Embaſſadours.</hi> This therefore is a 4th leſſon, which we may learn from a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon the certainty of Death; pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to undergo all ſickneſſes and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which are the neceſſary preliminaries and forerunners of it. But</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſtly, Another leſſon of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which may be taught us by a due reflection upon the certainty of Death, is this; that ſince that is the end of all men and nothing can qualify us for an exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from it, we ought therefore to bear the loſs of our Friends or our Relations, without
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54284:13"/>any immoderate or exceſſive ſorrow for them.</p>
            <p>For why ſhould that violently afflict or diſcompoſe us, which we have all the reaſon in the world to expect? can we ſuppoſe, that our Friends ſhould be peculiarly excepted, out of the common lot of all mankind? or becauſe they are <hi>Ours</hi> muſt they therefore be <hi>Immortal?</hi> It was the comfort which a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther applied to himſelf, to lighten the loſs of an only Son, <hi>Scio me mortalem genuiſſe,</hi> I know that I begot him a mortal man; by having conſidered that he muſt once die, he was able to ſupport his Death whenſoever it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened; and this will not fail to have the ſame effect upon us, if we will but preſs it as homely upon our ſelves: all our care and endeavours are neceſſary and decent, to aſſiſt our ſick friends in order to their recovery; a becoming ſence of our own loſs of them, and a moderate ſorrow for them, is natural and commendable; but to carry our concern to an unreaſonable height, to be violent or extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant in our expreſſions of grief, to let it ſwell
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54284:14"/>beyond the limits of Reaſon and Chriſtianity; this is, as if we would arraign the providence of God, which has appointed that <hi>Death ſhould be the end of all men;</hi> or as if we expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that for our ſakes, our Friends ſhould be excepted out of that general Sentence, which has univerſally paſt upon all mankind: We ſhould conſider, that they have got the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the exchange, by being taken out of a miſerable world, to be admitted into a ſtate of happineſs and perfection; we ſhould prefer their advantage before our own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment, rejoycing at their removal into bliſs, tho we pay dearly for it by our own want of them; we may <hi>long to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt</hi> and them, but cannot be ſo ſelfiſh or uncharitable, as to wiſh them back again with us! we ſhould rejoyce that our <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions</hi> are in a better <hi>Society!</hi> and that our <hi>Friends</hi> are preferred into <hi>Angels!</hi> in a word, we ſhould have nothing ſo dear which we cannot reſign unto our God, or which we can deſire to be diſpoſed of better: He that by conſidering his latter End, has ſeriouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printep
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54284:14"/>printed in his mind, the unavoidable neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Death to all men, that it ſtrikes impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and will ſpare none, will beſt be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to practice this leſſon; will never be too much diſturbed, at ſuch an event as he always foreſaw; and for which he has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly been prepared, whether in <hi>himſelf</hi> or in <hi>others.</hi> This then is a fifth <hi>Aphoriſm</hi> of Wiſdom which may be learnt by a due reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the certainty of Death; that we ſhould reſtrain all exceſſive or immoderate ſorrow, for the loſs of our Friends or our deareſt Relations.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if the loſs be of an <hi>Extraordinary</hi> nature, if the <hi>Publick</hi> be a ſufferer as well as <hi>Private families,</hi> (as it is in <hi>that Great man</hi> whoſe <hi>Obſequies</hi> we now celebrate;) as ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is then <hi>moſt buſy</hi> and <hi>importunate,</hi> ſo ought we then moſt eſpecially <hi>to ſtand upon our guard;</hi> we ſhould Summon to our aſſiſtance what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may ſuſtain us, againſt the attempts of a grief <hi>ſo juſt and piercing.</hi> But God, <hi>who delights not to afflict the Children of men,</hi> has generally accompanied ſuch melancholy cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54284:15"/>with an <hi>Antidote</hi> ſufficient to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate their malevolence. The fame and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which ſuch perſons leave behind them, and which always ſhines cleareſt <hi>out of the land of Darkneſs,</hi> and ſtretches out with their dead bodies, uſually adminiſtring ſuch additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal conſolation, as may ſerve to buoy up the ſpirits of their friends, under the heavy preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their encroaching ſorrow. And if ever that comfort was abundantly indulged, it is now imparted in a moſt eminent degree, to the ſurviving lamenters of this departed <hi>Heroe;</hi> than whom, as none has gone to the Grave more univerſally regretted; ſo none will live more generally or more laſtingly, in the Remembrance and reſpect of all that knew him. And now, as I have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed my Duty to the <hi>Living,</hi> by ſhewing them what advantages may accrue to them, from a due reflection upon the certainty of Death; ſo give me leave, to aquit my ſelf in ſome meaſure of my reſpects <hi>to the Dead,</hi> by hinting to you ſome ſew of thoſe many excellencies, by which he was eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted very conſiderably, above the common
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54284:15"/>rank of men. But leſt too a great a variety of matter, ſhould make my diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and rambling; I ſhall therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine my imperfect character, to theſe three qualifications in which he was moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, of a Gentleman, a Patriot, and a Souldier.</p>
            <p>Firſt. Then, let us conſider him as a <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman;</hi> and we ſhall find him poſſeſſed of all thoſe accompliſhments, which intitle a man juſtly to that honourable appellation, and recommend him to univerſal eſteem. Beſides the felicity of an illuſtrious extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of an antienter date than the <hi>Norman</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt; (for which he afterwards over-paid his family, by imparting to it greater luſtre than he borrowed from it) he was ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly remarkable for thoſe commendable em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhments, which diſtinguiſh a man of ſenſe and breeding, from the leſs reſin'd part of human kind: His converſation was familiar and engaging, his wit lively and piercing, his judgment ſolid and diſcerning; and all theſe ſet off by a graceful perſon, a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54284:16"/>chearful aſpect, and an inviting air. his <hi>natural abilities</hi> were cultivated and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, by the <hi>additional advantages</hi> of <hi>Travel</hi> and <hi>Experience;</hi> to his own reputation and the credit of his Country, much of his <hi>youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful time</hi> did he ſpend <hi>abroad;</hi> by which his <hi>riper years</hi> were qualified, to become more uſeful and ſerviceable <hi>at home;</hi> he made it not his buſineſs, (as too many have done) to glean the <hi>follies</hi> and the <hi>weakneſſes</hi> of thoſe Nations he converſed with, and to traffick only in <hi>Bells</hi> and <hi>Bawbles:</hi> but imported ſuch things as deſerved his application, and inriched his mind with their <hi>moſt valuable Commodities:</hi> He pryed into their <hi>cuſtoms,</hi> their <hi>politicks,</hi> and their <hi>ſtrength,</hi> without being partial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly byaſſed in their favour; returning, as he went out, <hi>a True Engliſhman;</hi> and valuing more highly the <hi>conſtitutions of his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> by comparing them with the miſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagements and irregularities which he had carefully obſerved <hi>in the Government of others:</hi> Thus did he wiſely endeavour to fit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, more for <hi>Service</hi> than for ſhew; look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54284:16"/>upon <hi>Language</hi> and <hi>faſhionable breeding</hi> (in which however he was verſed as well as any man) but as the becoming <hi>trappings</hi> and <hi>furniture,</hi> of his more <hi>conſiderable ſubſtantial improvements:</hi> Beſides all which he was particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly taken notice of, for a ſurprizing largeneſs and generoſity of Soul; ſuch as ſet him above the little temptations of private intriguings and narrow deſigns; being always ready to make his <hi>own intereſt truckle</hi> to the advantage of <hi>others,</hi> or the ſervice of the <hi>Publick:</hi> By ſuch methods as theſe he gain'd eſteem every where: and had the general commendation from all tongues of being, what ſo many aim at, and ſo few attain to <hi>a compleat</hi> Engliſh <hi>Gentleman.</hi> But</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us conſider him as <hi>a Patriot;</hi> and we ſhall find his affection to his native Country, to have been as diſintereſted, as it was firm and exemplary: His earlier years were ſpent abroad in her Service, and in the honourable fatigues of a foreign war; nor could all the allurements of royal favour (which would largely have been ſhowred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo conſiderable a man) bribe him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to forſake her cauſe, or to eſpouſe a Party oppoſite to her intereſts; he ſtuck cloſe to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54284:17"/>his <hi>Honour,</hi> and to his <hi>Love to her,</hi> tho at the expence of a valuable <hi>employment,</hi> and much more valuable <hi>expectations;</hi> he laid down his Commiſſion with a chearful reſignation, when he could no longer keep it without diſſerving her, for whoſe ſake and ſafety he accepted it before; and expoſed himſelf readily to a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary baniſhment, rather than he would be a ſpectator to thoſe miſeries, which were about to exerciſe his native land, and to which he could <hi>then</hi> apply no remedy: ſince that how vigoroyſly did he contribute his aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to our <hi>late happy Revolution!</hi> and how firm and unalterable has his adherence been, to <hi>the beſt of Princes and of Governments!</hi> and all this, without being acted by thoſe little motives, of advancing his fortune, or his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in the world; but receiving all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved preferments, as the favours of a Prince whom he valued more, for his perſonal ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues than for his royal Bounties; and only eſteeming them as the inſtruments and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, of being more ſignally and ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſeful to his Country. How freely ever after did be expoſe himſelf to danger, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever her honour or advantage called upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54284:17"/>him! till at laſt he ſealed his tenderneſs for her, with the higheſt expreſſion of it that could be given, <hi>Greater love than this has no man, that he lay down his Life!</hi> This did he for <hi>his dear Country,</hi> fighting in her cauſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her moſt powerful and moſt inveterate enemies; and teſtified a ſenſible concern at his Death, <hi>that he had not another life to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, for the advancement of her intereſt and the ſervice of his Prince:</hi> and he met with a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful return of love; ſince few, if any, have ever had the happineſs, to be ſo much <hi>the Darling of all ſorts of people,</hi> or to be attended to their grave with ſo general a ſorrow, But</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us conſider him as a <hi>Souldier</hi> and here we ſhall find him vigorous and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive; ſurprizingly brave in the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous emergencies; and eagerly catching at all opportunities, in which he might ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize his <hi>Courage</hi> without forfeiting his <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> If all the other actions of his life were ſilent, <hi>Athlone</hi> would ſpeak both his <hi>Valour</hi> and his <hi>Conduct;</hi> an action, in which I know not whether was more wonderful, the <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,</hi> or the <hi>Execution; both of them were admirable, and both his own. I</hi> appeal to thoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54284:18"/>who were under his Command if he ever. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to take the firſt Eſſay of danger; or, addreſſed to them in other Language than that of the great <hi>Julius,</hi> who requited, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected nothing more from his Legions, than that <hi>they would follow where he led the way:</hi> and yet, with all this ardour of an invincible cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, he was not of an uneaſy turbulent diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, or overapt to be engaged in <hi>idle</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels; for as the ſweetneſs of his nature, and; the politeneſs of his education, hindered him from offering an affront to any man; ſo the modeſt ſenſe which he had of his own juſt merit, would not ſuffer him to ſuſpect, that he was deſigned upon by others; the <hi>Fire</hi> then of his temper worked calmly and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, like that <hi>vital warmth</hi> which cheriſhes the body, and is ſubſervient to the great ends of <hi>health and livelineſs;</hi> whilſt that of too many others, reſembles the <hi>malignant heat of a Feaver,</hi> which boils up into <hi>folly and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> He loved all Souldiers, he lived amongſt them, and he died like one; and ſince he was no leſs beloved by them, I have hopes that the deſire of revenging his death, may prove a ſharper Spur to their future Undertakings,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54284:18"/>than even <hi>his preſence</hi> formerly and <hi>great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample;</hi> that ſo the juſt anger which his loſs works in them (the loſs of a <hi>Patron</hi> as well as of <hi>a Leader</hi>) may ſend thouſands of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries to wait upon his Ghoſt, and make <hi>Sampſon's</hi> character be applicable to him, <hi>that the Enemies which he deſtroyed by his Death, were more than thoſe which he ſlew in his Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I acted like that <hi>Painter,</hi> who drawing the picture of a <hi>young Noble-man</hi> ſome days after he was buried, was fain to fall vaſtly ſhort of the <hi>beautiful Original,</hi> and could only copy out <hi>a very faint reſemblance:</hi> in like manner have I dealt with <hi>my preſent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject;</hi> giving you only <hi>ſome imperfect lines,</hi> by which you may be juſt able to <hi>gueſs at the party.</hi> Such then, as <hi>fame</hi> and <hi>your own knowledge</hi> will more fully <hi>decipher him</hi> was <hi>this Great man,</hi> who is now but a cold neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected lump of Clay: Death, <hi>which is the end of all men,</hi> has aſſerted its Juriſdiction over <hi>him</hi> alſo; I mean, over as much of him as could dye; for his unblemiſhed reputation is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from mortality, <hi>Death has no farther dominion over him.</hi> Tho his <hi>carcaſs</hi> muſt be conſigned to <hi>worms and putrefaction,</hi> yet the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54284:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>memory</hi> of his great actions ſhall for ever <hi>live and flouriſh;</hi> in whatſoever parts of the earth, <hi>an accompliſhed Gentleman, a zealous Lover of his Country, or a deſerving Commander</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred with reſpect the name of <hi>Tolmach</hi> who was eminently all theſe, ſhall never fail of an honourable mention.</p>
            <p>Let us then attend him to his Grave with decent expreſſions of a <hi>manly</hi> ſorrow; let no mixture interfere of <hi>weakneſs</hi> or <hi>eſſeminacy;</hi> nothing unbecoming the perſon we mourn for: but let us take our leave of him at the Dormitory of his Anceſtors, with the Prophet's Lamentation, <hi>Alas my Brother!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let us, who are yet living, ſo duly and ſeriouſly <hi>lay to heart,</hi> not only his end but that of all men elſe; that whenſoever this common lot of mankind, ſhall (as it once muſt) be ours in particular; we may leave behind (as he does) the odour of a good memory, and only exchange this life for a better. <hi>Which God of his infinite mercy grant we may all do through the merits and mediation of our bleſſed Redeemer, to whom with the Father and the Holy Spirit, be aſcribed all honour, power, might, majeſty and dominion, henceforth and for evermore,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
